בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is יז Yud-Zayin and we
pick up at the bottom of טז עמוד ב, Tet-Zayin amud bet,
the משנה. Mishna.
So we had mentioned a list of thirteen, thirteen שופרות, shofarot, which
is what we're eventually going to get to, which is they have
the sort of containers they put the money into. That's the reason
it was quoted.
Thirteen שולחנות, shulchanot, which are various tables, we'll see about that in
a minute, and thirteen prostrations, השתחויות. hishtachavayot. So actually the משנה Mishna
is now going to explain it sort of in
reverse. So it starts about the whole story about the fourteenth השתחויה
hishtachavaya and where it was seen by the ארון Aron was hidden,
and now we're going to talk about the thirteen and we're going
to, it's like an ABC and then CBA. Now we're going to
explain the השתחויות hishtachavayot and then we're going to explain the שולחנות
shulchanot and then eventually the שופרות. shofarot. So our משנה Mishna picks
up on the השתחויות. hishtachavayot. So let's take a look.
היכן היו השתחויות הללו? Heichan hayu hishtachavayot ellu? Where were these prostrations?
ארבע בצפון, arba batzafon, four in the north; וארבע בדרום, v'arba badarom,
four in the south; שלוש במזרח, shalosh bamizrach, three in the east;
ושתיים במערב, ush'tayim bama'arav, and two in the west. And this is
in the עזרה, Azarah, and we'll see in a minute what this
corresponds to. כנגדן שלוש עשרה שערים, K'negedan shlosh esrei sh'arim, and corresponding
to
the thirteen gates that they had in the עזרה. Azarah. דרומיים סמוכים
למערב, Dromiyim smuchim l'ma'arav, and now we're going to list them. The
southern ones starting in the west, so starting in the southwest corner
and going from southwest to southeast on the southern wall was the
following: שער העליון, Sha'ar ha'elyon, the upper gate; שער הדלק, Sha'ar hadelek,
the gate of lighting, of fire, of fuel. I'm going to give
you a diagram in a minute. שער הבכורות, Sha'ar habechorot, the one
for the firstborns; and שער המים, Sha'ar hamayim, the one for water.
So I have a little bit firstborn and the cattle?
Yeah, for, so here I have a picture here. It came with
my little iPad rather than printing out paper. Hold on, here we
go, from Hebrew Wikipedia, always a good source. You get a lot
of Hebrew Wikipedia. Whoops, see that? Can everybody see that? My face
would have been better. Okay, so all these things with the blues
are the gates. Okay, so if you start at the south, which
is here, and you start at the southwest, which is over there.
So let's see if it has it listed. Yeah, שער העליון, Sha'ar
ha'elyon, it's got it even listed. It's got a thing, this is
שער העליון, Sha'ar ha'elyon, שער הדלק, Sha'ar hadelek, and שער הבכורות, Sha'ar
habechorot, and ה hey is שער המים. Sha'ar hamayim. Okay, so these
four along
the southwest walls entering into the עזרה, Azarah, into the courtyard.
If I'm not mistaken, תפארת ישראל ויכין ובועז Tiferet Yisrael v'Yachin v'Boaz
on some of the משניות mishnayot has that.
Exactly, in מדות, Middot, there are, yes, in מדות Middot there's that
very big diagram. Yes, that is correct.
That is correct. So did the people do this
every time they passed one of them? What? So it's, no, it
sounds like it's a very good question, right? It sounds like that
everybody would regularly do this, and where would you do this because
who was allowed anyway in that area, it would only be the
כהנים? Kohanim? Is it sort of saying that whenever you went up
to הר הבית, Har habayit, did it, it was like on the
outside of the מקדש Mikdash and you was opposite, like not in
front of but opposite? Yeah, it's not clear because I was wondering
the exact same thing. I mean, who is allowed in this space,
basically the כהנים Kohanim only? And it spoke about, now it did
speak about חנניה סגן הכהנים Chananya sgan ha-Kohanim would do fourteen, which
also spoke about
רבן גמליאל. Rabban Gamliel. So it's not exactly clear where they were
when they were doing the bowing downs. So that is a very
good question.
What's a סגן? sgan? What is that?
A סגן sgan is like an assistant. Well, I know, but
let's not worry about it. I'm just saying. Okay, other places that
gets elaborated on. Okay, so let's take a look. Now if you
take a look, for example, why are these named this and this
gets to this question about what they would be used for, right?
Take a look here, for example, at the קרבן העדה, Korban ha-edah,
where he says at the bottom of the page, he
says שער העליון הוא שער סמוך למערב. Sha'ar ha'elyon hu sha'ar samuch
l'ma'arav. Okay, then he says דאחריו שער דלק כנגד לשכת העצים שהיתה
בעזרה, D'achrav sha'ar delek k'neged lishkat ha'etzim she-hayta ba-Azarah, בדרך שם היו
מכניסים שם עצי המערכה שדוחפים על גבי מזבח, B'derech sham hayu machnisim
sham atzei hamarakha she-dochfim al gabei mizbeach, they take
out the wood. שער הבכורות שמכניסים שם הבכורות שנשחטין בדרום. Sha'ar habechorot
she-machnisim sham habechorot she-nishchatin badarom. So but funny thing is that really,
if you had a קרבן, korban, a בכור, bechor, you would go
straight into here? You wouldn't have to go into here and wait
like in the עזרת ישראל? Ezrat Yisrael? I mean normally we assume
you go in the שער ניקנור Sha'ar Nicanor here and wait in
the עזרת ישראל Ezrat Yisrael and the כהנים Kohanim would come. So
does it really mean you would come up this way? That's very
strange. I mean, maybe if they were opening up into the עזרת
נשים, Ezrat Nashim, you would understand because you go in this way
and then ultimately you come in the front door. And when it
says שער הדלק, Sha'ar hadelek, well, I've got to tell you, the
לשכת הדלק lishkat hadelek is like one of these over here in
the עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim is where they kept the firewood. So
I have to be honest that I really don't understand what's going
on here. You know, why is the שער הדלק Sha'ar HaDelek distinct
from the לשכת הדלק? Lishkat HaDelek? Why are these שערים Shearim here?
Presumably, and normally ישראל Yisrael would go in here. Now, it's possible
maybe you went in and then you went around in the... like
there was like a narrow causeway, you know, all the way around,
but even that would be strange, going in here and then going
all the way around to the... I so I really don't, I
must say I don't fully understand the placement here.
Perhaps the שער הבכורות Sha'ar HaBechorot is because the בכורות, bechorot, בכורים
bechorim
animals were sacrificed in the southern...
Yeah, yeah, so that's what... yeah, that's what the קרבן העדה Korban
HaEdah says. It's true, but does that mean that if you had
a בכור, bechor, you'd go straight in here and a כהן kohen
would pick it up from you and שחט shacht it here?
Well, you can שחט shacht it...
All right, all right, but what I'm saying is that were you
able to bring it straight into the עזרה Azarah here? Maybe the
answer is yes. The implication... I mean, I know, but it's very
strange. We normally don't think about that, right? That you could come
straight into the עזרה Azarah on the side and not through the
front door, and a כהן kohen would come pick it up from
you there? Right? But even the idea of the שער הדלק. Sha'ar
HaDelek. I mean, is one of these rooms presumably was the לשכה
Lishka where they kept the wood? Right.
So I don't know. We could speculate. Okay, so now let's take
a look. ולמה נקרא שמו שער המים? Velamah nikra shemo Sha'ar HaMayim?
Why was it called the שער המים? Sha'ar HaMayim? Thank you. שבו
מכניסים צלוחית של מים בחג. Shebo machnisim tzluchit shel mayim beChag. That's
where they would bring in the water for the ניסוך המים Nisuch
HaMayim on סוכות. Sukkot. Of course, if you read the whole משניות
mishnayot in סוכה, Sukkah, it seems like on סוכות Sukkot when they
had the whole, you know, שמחת בית השואבה Simchat Beit HaShoevah and
all of... not the שמחת בית... Bayit. but whatever, the whole production
and the drawing of the water, that it would, if I'm remembering
correctly, I didn't double-check, that they would do a whole procession through
the עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim, right? And here it has you coming
through the שער המים. Sha'ar HaMayim. Again, you're coming through the side.
I don't know, maybe these were in the עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim,
but the assumption here is that these were in the עזרה Azarah
proper. Okay. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר: Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer:
בו המים מפכין. Bo hamayim mifachin. From there the water will be
מפכין, mifachin, which some mean poured out like from a פך, pach,
from a vessel, from a jug. ועתידין להיות יוצאין מתחת מפתן הבית.
Ve'atidin lihyot yotzin mitachat miftan habayit. And it will eventually be coming
out from under the like the מפתן, miftan, the threshold of the
בית. bayis, He's alluding to a פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל Yechezkel which
the גמרא Gemara is going to spend most of the דף daf
elaborating on for his vision לעתיד לבוא. le'atid lavo.
ומתן בצפונה. U'matan batzafonah. Up these four in the north. סמוכים במערב.
Smuchim bama'arav. Starting from the northwest, again, from the back of the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, from where the קודש קדשים Kodesh Kodashim is.
שער יכניה, Sha'ar Yechanyah, the gate of יכניה. Yechanyah. We'll talk about
why it was named after him. Specifically because he basically what? He
well, also, we'll see according to the גמרא, Gemara, he went in
there and he bowed down there before he was taken into exile.
שער הקרבן. Sha'ar HaKorban. I mean, then it was destroyed and rebuilt
but it was named after him. שער הקרבן, Sha'ar HaKorban, the gate
of the קרבן. Korban. Why of all things that one is called
the שער הקרבן? Sha'ar HaKorban? We'll take a look. Because anyway, but
the... but the point is that it says that's where you bring
in the קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, which are שחטed shacht in the
north. But again, according to this picture, you're going to bring a
קרבן korban in... I don't know if people see it. You're going
to bring a קרבן korban in here. First of all, שחיטתן בצפון
shchitaton batzafon was north of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. It didn't... you know,
it was over here. So you bring it in there, but again,
you, a סתם ישראל, stam Yisrael, is going to bring your קדשי
קדשים kodshei kodashim there? We normally assume you go from the front
door and the כהן kohen just takes it a little bit to
the north of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. You know? So this whole thing
I don't get, unless it's just to signify that the קדשים קדשים
kodashim kodashim are in the north, but it sounds like they were
used for this purpose. So I'm still not exactly getting the choreography
of how people brought their... would you really bring certain קרבנות korbanot
in the side doors? I mean, it would make for a more
efficient, you know, throughput if everybody didn't have to come through one
narrow opening, you had multiple people working at different places. Maybe they
just never actually stepped into the עזרה, Azarah, but they stood in
the gate and they handed their קרבן korban over. ישראל Yisrael would...
Normally, the normal assumption is that ישראל Yisrael would go up the
מעלות. maalot.
The normal assumption is that ישראל Yisrael would go here through שער
ניקנור. Sha'ar Nikanor. This is where the actual עזרת ישראל Ezrat Yisrael
begins, and they'd have 11 אמות amot till this black line to
stand, and from that point on, it was the כהנים. Kohanim. Okay?
And now we start talking about using all of these gates down
here and up here. It's a little strange.
Okay. שער הקרבן, שער הנשים. Sha'ar HaKorban, Sha'ar HaNashim. The women's gate.
Look at that, again the women. So if you take a look
at the קרבן העדה, Korban HaEdah, שבו הנשים נכנסות לסמוך על הקרבן,
shebo hanashim nichnasot lismoch al hakorban, אי נמי לעמוד על הקרבן. i
nami la'amod al hakorban. So this is the whole issue of סמיכה.
smicha. Interesting that he mentions that, there's a whole debate about women
doing סמיכה smicha on קרבנות korbanot or just to be with their
קרבנות, korbanot, to bring their קרבנות. korbanot. So now there's a separate
gate for women to go in, sounds like, you know, separate men's
and women's entrances. But again, it's not normally what you assume because
this is the עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim. you know, and women presumably
we always understood that women come through שער ניקנור. Sha'ar Nikanor. And
according to this, it's got... this thing here called שער הנשים Sha'ar
HaNashim way up here.
So. Steinsaltz says that women did סמיכה smicha and that was why
they came in.
Steinsaltz is just translating the משנה.
Mishna. I know, I know. He doesn't even bring any other... All
right. But let's say they're קיני לידה kinei leida or something like
that?
Yeah, could be, but that they דוקא davka came in so again,
I'm just trying to understand,
they came in and they actually entered into the עזרה, azara, they
handed it off to the כהן? kohein? I mean what would they...
They came in and stepped in,
which one of those is which שער sha'ar based on...
What? This is שער הנשים. Sha'ar HaNashim. Right. And then the other
one is...
This is, we're going to get to it, that's number four. Okay.
Do you say this is more authentic than the בבלי? Bavli? Well,
it's משנה Mishna certainly it's earlier, and it does seem to be
like I said, more just about recording data, but you have to
check it against the משניות mishnayot in מדות, Middot, because the משניות
mishnayot in מדות Middot also describe the whole construction. Okay. And this...
Does it disagree with it?
I have not done the check. I assume, I think that they're
basically in parallel, but I think the question that's not fully explicated
is a, where exactly were these gates? Were they here, maybe they
were here opposite the מזבח, mizbeach, number, and number two, number one,
number two is what were they actually used for? We just know
their names, right? What were they actually used for? You have to
see where the earliest material on that is. Is it Tannaic, is
it, is it in the גמרא? Gemara? So we have to like
sort of do more research to get a clearer answer. Yes.
Is it possible that the whole southern section was a later addition?
What do you mean? You mean the gates were a later
addition? I mean they always had an area like this, a courtyard
around the...
yeah, this whole southern... this whole section.
Oh, this? Oh, not the southern, the eastern, the עזרת נשים. Ezrat
Nashim?
Yeah. Southern, huh?
This? The עזרת נשים? Ezrat Nashim Yeah. This part, that's east. Okay.
This is north. Okay. Yeah. Well, the עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim certainly
is not part of the מקדש Mikdash proper. It doesn't have קדושת
המקדש, kedushat HaMikdash, it has קדושת הר הבית. kedushat Har HaBayit.
So I'm wondering if that was a later, like is it possible
that this משנה mishna refers only to that original, to the... what
would that be?
To the עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim, area? Yeah. That's what I was
wondering but it doesn't sound like it, it sounds like we're going
around the עזרה. azara. I mean we'll see in a minute.
Okay. And the other question I have is everything we're reading Herodian?
Well, yes, presumably. Yes.
Okay, so that's...
right. Right. Okay, so let's take a look.
שער הקרבן, Sha'ar HaKorban, שער הנשים, Sha'ar HaNashim, שער השיר. Sha'ar HaShir.
And the last one was called the שער השיר. Sha'ar HaShir. למד-ו'
Lamed-Vav now it says, explains this: one of them, ולמה נקרא שמו
שער יכניה velama nikra shemo Sha'ar Yechanya שבו יצא יכניה בגלותו? shebo
yatza Yechanya begaluto? That's the one he exited, now this is he
actually exited the gate when he was taken out into גלות. galut.
The גמרא Gemara has a slightly different version of that. What was
שער השיר Sha'ar HaShir now? It presumably is where they kept the,
what do you call it, the various musical instruments. They kept the...
What? They kept it... Yeah, it wasn't just a gate, like it
was a gate that had a room, which is... I mean, this
is also here, this is like you see they made it more
like a room, this one. Okay. And actually it's also presumably the
same as the בית המוקד, Beit HaMoked, which is where they kept
the regular fire going that the כהנים kohanim could get in that
room and warm themselves up in. Okay. So that was also that
space over there was used for that.
Like a לשכה lishka of sorts.
Yeah, so it was a combination of a לשכה lishka and a
gate.
Okay,
so now... שבמזרח, shebemizrach, in the east, שער ניקנור ושני פשפשים היו
לו. Sha'ar Nikanor veshnay pashpashim hayu lo. The gate of Nikanor and
there were two little side gates on the side, that gets you
counted as three. אחד מימינו ואחד משמאלו. echad mimino ve'echad mismolo. And
they didn't have a name. So that is why it looks like
we're going around the עזרה, azara, because the east here is, right,
it's not we're talking about some opening to שער הנשים, Sha'ar HaNashim,
the east is just the שער ניקנור Sha'ar Nikanor the main entrance
into the עזרה azara with the two little sides. And then it
says, ושנים במערב לא היה להם שם. veshenayim bema'arav lo haya lahem
shem. And two in the west, right, behind the קדש הקדשים, Kodesh
HaKodashim, which did not have any name. I remember once that we
had, I was talking to a woman who was visiting from Israel
and she said like, you know, she says like you just don't
appreciate like how you know both sort of steeped in history and
limited
geography there is in Israel. Like I was looking at a map
here in America and it had a little river or creek and
it had no name. She says in Israel you wouldn't have something
that had no name. They'd have four different names all symbolizing all
different stages of history and debating what to name it. So anyway
so actually here you have anyway two in the west had no
name on them. All right, so let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara. מתניתין. Matnitin. אבא יוסי בן יוחנן היא דאמר כנגד י"ג
שערים. Abba Yose ben Yochanan hi de'amar keneged yud-gimmel she'arin. He said
the prostrations were opposite, now again opposite means corresponding to or literally
in front of. It sounds like in front of, because before we
had that the fourteenth was in front of the place where the
you know where the לשכת העצים Lishkat Ha'Etzim where they thought the
ארון aron was buried. So again, are they in the עזרה azara
when they're bowing down? Are they opposite it but outside of the
עזרה? azara? Anyway, it was opposite or corresponding to the 13 gates.
רמי לרבנן, Ramy le-Rabbanan, but the Rabbis say, שבעה שערים היו בעזרה.
shiva she'arin hayu ba'azara. Notice again the... בעזרה, BaAzarah, right? So clearly
the גמרא Gemara understands that we're talking about the gates around the
עזרה Azarah proper. The Rabbis said there were not thirteen, there were
only seven. Now, I don't know exactly how you get that, you
could basically not count the last two if they don't have a
name, you could not count the two by the side of the
שער ניקנור, Sha'ar Nicanor, and then maybe some of them were actually
debated, but now it's a very interesting... how do you debate facts?
Okay, all right, anyway, but maybe they did, there was a question
about what the tradition was. אדעתא דרבנן Ada'ata Derabbanan היכן היו השתחוויות
הללו? heichan hayu hishtachavuyot hallalu? So
according to the Rabbis, where were the prostrations if they weren't opposite
the seven gates? So it sounds like it's actually physically where were
they. כהיא דתנינא תמן, Kehi detanina taman, like that which we taught
over there.
י"ג פרצות היו בה. Yud Gimmel peratzot hayu bah. There were thirteen
breaches in the
wall שפרצום מלכי יוון. sheperatzum malchei Yavan. How appropriate, Rosh Chodesh Kislev,
where we have a reference here to the period of the חשמונאים
Chashmonaim when the Greek king went ahead and... breached, thank you, that's
the word, breached the wall.
So there were thirteen places וחזרו וגדרום בני חשמונאי vechazru ugedarum benei
Chashmonai and the Chashmonaim went and they
went ahead and they rebuilt it.
ובגזרו כנגדן י"ג השתחוויות Uvegazru kenegdan yud gimmel hishtachavuyot and they established
opposite them thirteen prostrations. Again, does it mean כנגדן kenegdan meaning corresponding
to them or כנגדן kenegdan sounds like actually in front of them
in those places? Which is actually interesting, you know, if you think
about it, why to evoke the idea of השתחוואה hishtachavayah in a
place of, you know, which actually sort of symbolized the sense of
being breached, like something, you know, but maybe often you pray because
you want things to be better. So here it sort of evokes
that sense that there was, you
know, a hard time, there was persecution, and ultimately we persevere. It's
interesting thinking about, right, it's interesting thinking about the symbolism of bowing
down opposite the places of the breach. As opposed to, yeah, they've
never been bowing down before that.
Well, maybe they'd bow down seven times, maybe they didn't do it
thirteen, we don't know, like you know, but the idea that there's
going to be thirteen places, right, you know, it seems to be
right, it doesn't sound like there was no bowing down, but the
idea of thirteen and opposite or in front of these places. Okay,
now because we mentioned this שער המים Sha'ar HaMayim and בו המים
מפכים, bo hamayim mepachim, we're going to read these פסוקים pesukim from
יחזקאל. Yechezkel. We'll start with a פסוק pasuk from זכריה Zecharyah and
about water eventually coming out of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and
that's going to be most of the דף. daf. So let's start
with the פסוק pasuk in זכריה. Zecharyah. כתיב והיה ביום ההוא יצאו
מים חיים מירושלים. Ketiv vehayah bayom hahu yetze'u mayim chayim miYerushalayim. On
that day the living waters will come out of Jerusalem. תני ותניא
בברייתא, Tani vetanya bivraita, מבית קדשי קדשים עד הפרוכת. Mibeit kodshei kodashim
ad haparochet. So here's how it's going to flow: it's going to
start in the Holy of Holies and it's going to grow, the
stream as it gets further. Underground, right? Well, no, it doesn't sound
like it's underground. Well, let's take a
look. So מבית קדשי קדשים עד הפרוכת, Mibeit kodshei kodashim ad haparochet,
כקרני סילי וחילי. kekarnei silei vechilei. It'll be like the horns of
these like small, you know, like the antenna of these small insects.
I don't know, what do they translate what those insects
are? Whatever. No, whatever.
Small insects. סילי וחילי.
Silei vechilei. ששין השרץ? Sashin Hasheretz? Right. Oh, that's interesting, the idea
of קרן. keren. מהפרוכת ועד מזבח הזהב. Mehaparohet ve'ad mizbe'ach hazahav. That's
snails?
Snails.
Ah, okay, snails. Ah, good, that makes sense. Okay, snail antenna. מהפרוכת
ועד מזבח הזהב, Mehaparohet ve'ad mizbe'ach hazahav, from the curtain until the
golden altar, which was in the קודש, Kodesh, right opposite the מנורה
Menorah and the שולחן. Shulchan. כקרני חגבים, Kekarnei chagavim, it's like the
antenna of grasshoppers, which is a little thicker, so the stream is
growing. ממזבח הזהב ועד עזרה, Mimizbe'ach hazahav ve'ad azarah, from the golden
altar until the עזרה, Azarah, presumably including עזרת נשים, so as it
now flows and is about to exit the structure, goes through the
עזרה, Azarah, כחוט של שתי. kechut shel sheti. It's like—it's like a
string of warp, which is the thinner of the strings of the
warp and the woof. Or maybe it's woof. I keep on getting
confused which is which. I think that's warp. Anyway, מן העזרה ועד
מפתן הבית, Min ha'azarah ve'ad miftan habayit, from the עזרה Azarah until
the threshold, כחוט של ערב, kechut shel erev, that's like the woof,
that's a little bit thicker. מכאן ואילך, Mikan va'eilach, from that point
on, כפי הפך, kepi hapach, it's like being poured out of a
jar and that's the word in the משנה, Mishnah, מפכים, mepachim, from
the פך. pach. It's like poured out of a jar. Right when
he mentions the מפתן הבית miftan habayit also. כתיב. Ketiv. Okay, so
now we're going to look at a verse that talks about this.
I do want to say before we look at the verse, it
is interesting, you know, normally you assume that sort of a sense
of the divine presence, right, is strongest in the קדשי קדשים Kodshei
Kodashim and it sort of gets more attenuated the further away you
get, whereas here you have the idea that this stream starts small
and it gets very, very large. And I mean that's true about
like rivers, right? You know, they actually start very small and then
further down, you know, they're roaring giant rivers.
Well, in terms of agreeing with the
service—well, yeah, I mean that's true. But in terms of the symbolism,
I'm wondering, you know,
it's like this symbolism of קול דממה דקה. kol demamah dakkah. קול
דממה דקה. kol demama daka.
Right. It's very similar. That's true. That's true. Now I want to
read you, I'm just going to read it to you in English,
we're going to read a lot of it in Hebrew, but I
want to give—but I want to give you a sense of what
we're sort of—of the פרק perek in יחזקאל Yichezkel that we're going
to be interpreting. Okay, so I'm—just thought it's just easier if I
read it quickly in English. Afterward he brought me, this angel, to
the door of the house, the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, behold, waters
issued out from under the threshold of the house eastwards. So that's
מזרח הבית, mizrach habayis, right? And the—the opening is in the east,
right, whatever, under—anyway, eastward, for the forefront of the house stood to
the east. Waters came down from the right side of the house,
so the right side is—would be—would be the north—no, the south, because
you're facing east. Right? You face east, so the right—your right would
be the south. At the south side of the altar. No—no, you
always assume—the—the reason east is קדם kedem is קדים, kadim,
it's—it's—it's the way—what you say to orient yourself is to face yourself
east, to face yourself towards the rising sun. So the right, right,
is always the south, and the left is always the north, which
is why תימנה teimana is the south, 'cause from the word ימין.
yamin. Then he brought me out of the way of the gate
northward, and led me—whatever, they ran out waters on the right side,
again the north. When the man that had a line in his
hand went forth eastward, he measured a thousand cubits, so now we're
measuring it as the waters continue east. And he brought me through
waters, the waters were to the ankles. He measured another thousand, brought
me through the waters, the waters were to the knees. He measured
another thousand, brought me through the waters, the waters were to the
loins. After he measured a thousand and it was a river that
I could not pass over, for the waters were risen, waters to
swim in, a river that could not be passed over. Okay, and
so now we'll—that's only half the פרק. perek. Now we're going to
read exactly that in the Hebrew here and interpret it, and then
we're going to get back to the other half of the פרק.
perek. So let's take a look. Okay, כתיב, ksiv, it says, והנה
מים מפכים, vehinei mayim mefachim,
so there's the word מפכים mefachim from פך, pach, pouring out like
a jug, מן הכתף הימנית, min hakasef hayemanis, from the right side
of the—of the בית, בצאת האיש קדים, betzeis haish kadim,
the man was going out in the east, וקו בידו, vekav beyado,
and he was carrying a—a measuring stick or a staff in his
hand. וימד אלף באמה, vayamod elef baamma,
he measured a thousand
אמה, ama, ויעבירני במים, vayaavireni bamayim, מי אפסיים, mei afsayim,
water to the ankles. So the גמרא Gemara now just says, what
does אפסיים afsayim mean? עד קרסולא, ad karsula, until the ankles. וימד
אלף, vayamod elef, he measured another thousand אמה, ama, ויעבירני במים, vayaavireni
bamayim, מי ברכיים, mei birkayim, and he passed me through waters that
went up to the knees. עד ארכובא, ad arkuba,
until the knees. Okay, וימד אלף ויעבירני מי מתניים, vayamod elef vayaavireni
mei masnayim,
to the loins. עד מתניא, ad masnya, till the—till the loins. You
wonder like why you're bothering to translate. Anyway, מכאן ואילך, mikan vaeilach,
that afterwards, וימד
אלף, vayamod elef, another thousand אמה, ama, נחל, nachal, a river, אשר
לא אוכל לעבור, asher lo uchal laavor, that I could not pass
through. So the גמרא Gemara says, אפילו לבורני, afilu levirani, even for—large
ships, גדולה אינה יכולה לעבור בו, gedola einah yecholah laavor bo, you
cannot pass through. מאי טעמא, mai taama, why? And now we quote
a פסוק pasuk from ישעיהו, Yeshayahu, so we sort of merge פסוקים
psukim together: וצי אדיר לא יעברנו, v’tzi adir lo yaavrenu, even a
great ship shall not pass through it. מפני מה, mipnei mah, why?
כי גאו המים מי שחו. ki ga’u hamayim mei sachu. This is
back to the פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל. Yichezkel. Because the waters were
very great, waters to swim in. מה מי שחו, mah mei sachu,
what does it mean waters to swim in? מלשוט, milashut, to swim.
אמר רבי חונא, amar Rabbi Chuna, באתרין, baasrin,
in our place, קרו לשייטא שחונא, karu lishayata sachuna, we call swimmers
שחונא. sachuna. So—so שחו sachu or שחונא. sachuna. שחו sachu means to
swim. Okay, but what's the ship though? What? No,
because that was also I think in the פסוק. pasuk.
Waters to swim in, a—a river that cannot be passed over. So
it can't be passed over, presumably means even a ship. ופרש ידיו
בקרבו. ufaras yadav bekirbo.
Now again, this is the פסוק pasuk in ישעיהו, Yeshayahu, not from
יחזקאל, Yichezkel, but it's to demonstrate the idea that לשוח lasuach means
to swim. He spread his hands inside of him, כאשר יפרש השוח
לשחות, kaasher yifares hasocheh lischos,
like a swimmer, I guess if you're doing the butterfly stroke or
something would do to swim, would stretch out his arms inside and
outside to swim. So you see לשחות lischos means to—to—to swim. Now
although we said it means to swim, we're going to have another
דרשה drasha on it, מהו לשחות mahu lischos or some have the
גרסא girsa מהו מי שחו, mahu mei sachu, waters of swimming, אמר
רבי יוסי בריה דרבי בון, amar Rabbi Yosi brei d’Rabbi Bun, מים
דמיסתלעין בעלמא. mayim demistalin bealma. So the word not from לשחות lischos
to swim but שיח siach to speak, right? שיח siach means to
speak. So waters that will be spoken about throughout the world, because
we're going to see that these are going to be miraculous waters.
Okay, כתיב, ksiv, now back—now a פסוק pasuk in זכריה, Zechariah, we're
sort of tying together multiple prophecies about water and the future like,
you know, flowing water out of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay,
ביום ההוא, bayom hahu, on that day, this is now from זכריה,
Zechariah, we'll get back to יחזקאל Yichezkel in a minute, on that
day יהיה מקור נפתח לבית דויד, yihiyeh makor niftach l’veis David, it
will be a wellspring opened up for the house of David, וליושבי
ירושלים, ulyoshvei Yerushalayim, those who dwell in Jerusalem, לחטאת ולנדה, l’chatas ulenidah,
for חטאת, chatas, which could mean sin-offering, could mean the פרה אדומה
parah adumah is called a חטאת, chatas, which is how the גמרא
Gemara will read it, or sinners, and for נדה, nidah, literally menstruant
women. So what does that mean? So the גמרא Gemara understands, if
you're talking about water and talking about a נדה nidah and a
חטאת, chatas, it must be that you're talking about using this for
ritual purposes.
אמר רבי שמואל בר נחמני בשם רבי יונתן, amar Rabbi Shmuel bar
Nachmani beshem Rabbi Yonasan, מבית דוד ועד יושבי ירושלים, mibeis David v’ad
yoshvei Yerushalayim, for—for... So as the water flows from the king's house
throughout ירושלים Yerushalayim *Yerushalayim*, same water in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
*Beit
HaMikdash*? Yeah presumably it's conflating them all. So now it's coming out
of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash*, it flows to the
king's house and from there throughout ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, so כשרים לנדה ולחטאת
*kesherim le-niddah ve-la-chatat*. That is water that is from מים חיים *mayim
chayim*. It's coming from a live stream underground and therefore you can
use it for חטאת *chatat* for פרה אדומה *parah adumah* which you
can use מים חיים *mayim chayim*. No, you have to add the
ashes but the base ingredient of water of מים חיים *mayim chayim*
and a נדה *niddah* can and you know can go into it.
It's a מקוה *mikveh*?
I was going to ask but I thought it was you pass
through it, how they going to go into it if it's a
raging river?
Yeah that's a good question.
Maybe you could draw the water for מי חטאת *mei chatat* but
for the נדה *niddah* I don't know but you don't have to
actually pass through it, you just dunk in it and come out.
Just
make sure you have a life preserver.
I get underneath is it transforming the מקדש *Mikdash* to גן עדן
Gan Eden. *Gan Eden*, the water is the source of...
Aha, well actually I think that's in יחזקאל Yechezkel. *Yechezkel* because the
פסוקים psukim *psukim* go on and speak about all the trees that
are growing there. Right, so that's an interesting thought though about the
גן עדן Gan Eden. *Gan Eden* connection. I don't see it so
much yet in the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* but anyway. Okay מכאן ואילך
*mikan va-eilech* so from that point onwards, מי תערובות הם *mei ta'arovot
heim*, they are mixed waters, meaning after they leave ירושלים *Yerushalayim*, you
know rainwater will fall into them, other things will fall into them
and therefore it's not purely מים חיים *mayim chayim* and you cannot
use it. So כשרים לנדה... where was it? מי תערובות הם *mei
ta'arovot heim*, כשרים לנדה פסולים למי חטאת *kesherim le-niddah psulim le-mei chatat*.
So even though it has rainwater you can still use it for
a נדה *niddah* but you cannot use it for a חטאת *chatat*
anymore because it has other waters mixed into it. Okay so
okay one minute. אמר רבי אלעזר *Amar Rabbi Elazar*: No, he has
a different version, a different understanding. מבית דוד ועד יושבי ירושלים כשרים
לנדה ולחטאת *mi-Beit David ve-ad yoshvei Yerushalayim kesherim le-niddah ve-la-chatat* like you
said because then it's מים חיים *mayim chayim*. מכאן ואילך *mikan va-eilech*
from that point on, מי קטפרסות הם *mei katafresot heim*, they are
waters that run down at an angle. קטפרס *katafres* is an angle
like at a
slope. פסולים לנדה ולחטאת *psulim le-niddah ve-la-chatat*. Now since when? Why is
it פסול pasul. *pasul* for a נדה *niddah* just because it's running
down a slope? So the מפרשים *mefarshim* assume that what he's talking
about is he agrees that there's rainwater mixed in with it. But
if there's rainwater mixed in, the הלכה *halacha* is that if you
have a water, a river that has a majority of rainwater that
actually if you cannot use it for a מקוה *mikvah* because it's
running water and to use running water if it's the majority is
sort of underground water, live stream and so on it can be
running, if the majority is rainwater it has to be still. So
he says a נדה *niddah* actually can't use it because it would
be majority, it would still be mixed, he's assuming mixed, it would
be rainwater and therefore can't be running. So who cares about the
idea of the incline? Well because if it's connected to the you
know the part that does not have the mixed, that might make
it all considered sort of one unit, but if it runs at
an incline there's a whole discussion in the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* whether
קטפרס *katafres* is חיבור *chibur* or not. Water running down an incline,
is it connected to the water that's above the incline or are
they separate bodies of water? So presumably what you're saying is because
it will run down an incline and it'll be mixed with other
waters and it'll be running, it won't even be able to be
used for נדה *niddah* purposes. Okay so כתיב *ksiv* now back to
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*. ויאמר אלי *Vayomer elai*: so now back to
the פסוקים *psukim* in יחזקאל Yechezkel, *Yechezkel*. Here I'll read you a
little bit in English. He said to me, son of man, hast
thou seen this? Then he brought me and caused me to return
to the brink of the river. When I returned at the bank
of the river were very many trees on one side and the
other. And he said, these waters issue out towards the east country,
go down the desert, go to the sea, and being brought forth
into the sea the waters shall be healed. And it shall come
to pass that everything that lives which moves wheresoever the rivers come
shall live, and there shall be a great multitude of fish, there
you go Dov about the whole גן עדן *Gan Eden* because these
waters shall come to them, basically the waters will go into the
sea and it'll heal the sea rivers, it sounds like which are
salty and so on and it'll bring you know much life and
much fish. Okay and it speaks about how everybody will be able
to get millions of fish out of the out of the sea
now. And then it says, and here by the way continuing in
this גן עדן *Gan Eden* theme in the פסוקים *psukim*: And by
the river the bank the side that shall go the side on
that side shall go all trees for meat whose leaf shall not
fade, neither shall the fruit be consumed, it shall bring forth new
fruit according to its months because the waters they issued out of
the sanctuary, the fruit shall be for meat and the leaf for
medicine. Okay so let's take a look now as the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* explains those פסוקים *psukim*.
I think the מדרש Midrash, *Midrash* says there's the באר *be'er*...
Oh was it? Into the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
to draw water in הבדלה *Havdalah* that it was possibly drawing some
of the water from the בארה של מרים *be'erah
shel Miriam*?
Oh that's interesting. Okay that's interesting. I hadn't heard that. All right.
So let's ויאמר אלי *Vayomer elai*, so he said to me, now
back to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*: המים האלה יוצאים אל הגלילה הקדמונה
*ha-mayim ha-eileh yotzim el ha-Gelilah ha-Kadmonah*, these waters go to the east
country. Okay or זה *zeh*,
so what's the east country? גלילה Galilah.
*Gelilah* is a
country that's at least the... King James translates it. זה ים של
סמכו, Samcho. this is the גלילה הקדמונה Galilah hakadmonah is the ocean
of סמכו. Samcho Okay, it's going to imagine various seas, I mean
it calls everything an ocean, various seas and bodies of water that
surround Israel. I have no idea what this סמכו is supposed to
refer to.
רש"י Rashi says Hula Lake in the northern גלילה.
Interesting.
Okay, וירדו אל הערבה Vayerdu el Ha'aravah to the ערבה, Arabah, זה
ים של טבריה, ze yam shel Tiveria, that's Tiberias, the sea of
Tiberias, the Sea of כנרת, Kinneret, thank you. ובא בו הימה Uva
bo hayamah and it comes to the ocean or whatever, זה ים
המלח, ze yam hamelach, that's the Dead Sea. אל הימה המוצאים El
hayamah hamotzi'im and to the waters that go out or the ocean
that goes out, זה הים הגדול, ze hayam hagadol, that's the Mediterranean.
ולמה נקרא שמו מוצאים, Velamah nikra shemo motzi'im, why is it called
מוצאים? motzi'im? כנגד שתי פעמים שיצא Keneged shetei pe'amim sheyatza because the
Mediterranean went out of its boundaries, you know, twice in history. אחד
בדור אנוש, Echad bedor Enosh, one in the period of אנוש Enosh
according to the גמרא, Gemara they were, you know, the sinning of
the time of אנוש Enosh and the עבודה זרה avodah zarah led
to God sort of
drowning a third of the world. So apparently that was the Mediterranean
overflowing. וחד בדור הפלגה, Vechad bedor haflagah, at the time of the
Tower of בבל, Bavel, I don't know, somehow there was also some
flood going on there. I have no idea. Anyway, רבי אלעזר ברבי
בשם רבי חנינא, Rabbi Elazar berabbi beshem Rabbi Chanina, בראשונה יצא עד
קלבריא. Berishonah yatza ad Kalbareia. Originally it went out to קלבריא. Kalbareia.
קלבריא Kalbareia apparently is the name of some place where the דור
הפלגה dor haflagah took place.
The קרבן העדה Korban Ha'edah says it is in somewhere in France.
He says in southern Italy. Okay.
That guy's actually what it's called. There's an area in Calabria.
Calabria. Okay, ובשניה Uvasheniyah the second time, presumably in the דור הפלגה,
dor haflagah, יצא עד כיפי ברבריא yatza ad kapei Barbaria until the
shores of
ברבריא. Barbaria. Where's that? North Africa. North Africa. Barbary Coast. Okay, רבי
יעקב בשם רבי חנינא, Rabbi Ya'akov beshem Rabbi Chanina, בראשונה יצא עד
כיפי ברבריא, berishonah yatza kapei Barbaria, ובשניה, uvasheniyah, no, the first time
it went to
ברבריא, Barbaria, ובשניה, uvasheniyah, the second time, יצא עד עכו, yatza ad
Akko, it went until עכו, Akko, and ad יפו. Yafo. But I
don't get it because the Mediterranean is, does border on עכו Akko
and
יפו. Yafo. So yeah, maybe it means it just flooded those cities.
Maybe it wasn't there until then.
Or no, maybe it means it flooded those cities. Okay, עד פה,
ad poh, now we're just, now we're just starting a פסוק pasuk
in איוב Iyov to finish this. תבוא, Tavo, until here you should
come, ולא תוסיף velo tosif and not go any further. So עד
פה ad poh is עד עכו, ad Akko, it's a little play
on words, עד פה עכו. ad poh Akko. Okay. תבוא ולא תוסיף
ופה ישית גאון גליך, Tavo velo tosif upoh yashit geon galecha, you
should go until here and not increase, and here you shall put
the sort of haughtiness of your waves, the pride of your waves.
עד יפו ישית גאון גליך, Ad Yafo yashit geon galecha, so ופה
יפו. upoh Yafo. עד כה ad koh is עכו Akko and ופה
upoh is יפו. Yafo. Okay. Anyway, all of that was a little
digression from this river that is going to go through all of
the various seas and oceans that are around Israel on the דרשה
drasha on the פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל. Yechezkel. Now, ניחא ימא רבא
וימא דמילחא. Nicha yama raba veyama demilcha. I guess, says the גמרא,
Gemara why it's going to go into the Mediterranean and into the
ים המלח, Yam Hamelach, the Dead Sea, this river.
בשביל למתקן Bishvil lemitkan to fix the waters. Like the פסוק pasuk
says, it's sweet water and it'll come into the salty water. But
ימא דטבריא וימא דסמכו, yama deTiveria veyama deSamcho, so why do you
need it to go into the כנרת Kinneret and into what did
you say this ימא דסמכו yama deSamcho was?
Some other sea there, what did you say, whatever Charlie said it
was. Okay, anyway, why do you need it to go there? Those
are already sweet waters. So לרבות דגתם, lerabot dagatam, it doesn't need
to make the waters sweet, but it's in order to increase the
fish in the water. דכתיב ביה Dechtiv bei and now we quote
the פסוק pasuk that says that's exactly what it will do.
למינה תהיה דגתם, Leminah tihyeh dagatam, the fish will be to its
kind. What does that mean? למיני מיני תהיה דגתם, Leminei minei tihyeh
dagatam, the fish will be multitudes of different species of fish that
will now grow in these waters. Pretty ironic because in the ocean
you do have multitudes, so many species of fish, but I guess
if they didn't know that and if you go fishing in the
ocean you only get so many types of fish. Okay, so תניא
tania מתנא ברייתא, meitana baraita, אמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, amar Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel, מעשה שהלכתי לצידן, ma'aseh shehalachti leTzeidan, I went to
צידן Tzeidan והביאו לפני יותר משלש מאות מיני דגים בתמחוי אחד. vehevi'u
lefanay yoter mishelosh me'ot minei dagim betamchoi echad. They brought me more
than three hundred, one imagines three hundred is an exaggeration, three hundred
is usually an exaggeration number, more than three hundred types of different
species of fish all in one dish.
Okay, now back to the פסוק pasuk. in יחזקאל, ונרפאו המים, venirpe'u
hamayim, the waters will be
healed, בצאתיו וגבאיו ולא ירפאו למלח נתנו. betzeitav vegeva'av velo yerpu lemelach
nittanu. Okay, and בצאתיו betzeitav and גבאיו geva'av and they will not
be healed because they are given for salt. So the way that
again the English translates this is the swamps and marshes won't be
healed because you do need salt water, so those will be left
for salt water. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara says, כתיב ונרפאו המים,
ktiv venirpu hamayim, the beginning of the verse says the water will
be healed, ואתה אמרת ולא ירפאו, ve'atah amarta velo yerpu, and the
end of the verse says and they won't be healed. So presumably
the simple sense is that, you know, other, these other places won't
be healed, but everywhere else it will be. So the גמרא Gemara.
says no, ולא ירפאו המים. velo yerpu hamayim. So the גמרא Gemara.
says מקום הוא ושמו ולא ירפאו. makom hu ushemo velo yerpu. Okay,
ולא ירפאו Velo Yerpu doesn't mean it won't be healed, it means
that's the
name of the place, ולא ירפאו. Velo Yerpu. By the edge of
the river will grow on both sides all types of food trees.
לא יבול עלהו lo yibol alehu the leaf won't wither, ולא יתום
פריו v'lo yitom piryo the fruit will never cease. לחדשיו יבכר l'chadashav
yivaker it will blossom, it will bear forth fruit on its months.
גן עדן. Right. So that is גן עדן. Okay. So תני Tani
we taught in a ברייתא. Braisa. אמר רבי יהודה, Amar Rabbi Yehuda,
לפי שבעולם הזה lefi she'ba'olam hazeh תבואה עושה לשישה חודשים tvua osa
l'shisha chodashim nowadays it takes wheat grain six months to grow, ואילן
עושה לשנים עשר חודש v'ilan osa l'shneim asar chodesh and trees are
on a yearly cycle, it takes them a year to come out
with their new fruit. אבל לעתיד לבוא Aval l'asid lavo in the
future, תבואה עושה לחודש אחד tvua osa l'chodesh echad grain will come
in one month because it's a two to one
ratio there of the amount of time. ואילן עושה לשני חודשים V'ilan
osa l'shnei chodashim and a tree two months. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama?
לחדשיו יבכר L'chadashav yivaker its months it will bring forth. So I
understand it means every two months it will bring forth new fruit.
So if a tree is doing it in two months, then and
it takes grain half as long as a tree to ripen, then
grain will ripen in one month. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosi,
לפי שבעולם הזה lefi she'ba'olam hazeh so now Rabbi Yosi outdo everyone
else. In this world, התבואה עושה שישה חודשים ha'tvua osa shisha chodashim
אילן עושה לשנים עשר חודש. ilan osa l'shneim asar chodesh. אבל לעתיד
לבוא Aval l'asid lavo in the future, התבואה עושה לטו יום ha'tvua
osa l'tet-vav yom it's not going to take a month for the
grain to ripen, it'll only take fifteen days.
ואילן עושה לחודש V'ilan osa l'chodesh and a tree will take a
month. לחדשיו L'chadashav means each one according to its month or every
month, but not two months. לחודש אחד. L'chodesh echad. שכן מצינו Shechen
matzinu and I'll prove it to you. שעשה תבואה בימי יואל לחמישה
עשר יום she'asa tvua bimei Yoel l'chamisha asar yom in Yoel there
was a miracle and the grain grew in fifteen days. וקרבו ממנו
עומר V'kirvu mimeno omer they brought the עומר. omer. מאי טעמא? Mai
ta'ama? How do you know? Because the פסוק pasuk says, ובני ציון
גילו ושמחו בה' אלוהיכם כי נתן לכם את המורה לצדקה u'vnei Tziyon
gilu v'simchu b'Hashem Elokeichem ki nasan lachem es hamoreh litzdaka He gave
you the early rain for righteousness, ויורד לכם גשם מורה ומלקוש בראשון
v'yored lachem geshem moreh u'malkosh barishon and the rain came down early
and late in the first, which presumably means ניסן. Nissan. Okay, and
therefore and presumably understands that it came down in ניסן Nissan and
they were rejoicing because now they're getting to bring the עומר omer
fifteen days later. So you see that it's possible in fifteen days
and therefore it will be that way in the future as well.
Grain is seen as a mini tree like עץ הדעת Etz HaDa'as
right
according to those that say that the עץ etz was תבואה. tvua.
Right. That's a good point to remind us that according to the
מדרש, Midrash, one מדרש, the עץ הדעת Etz HaDa'as was תבואה. tvua.
So the גמרא Gemara says, ומה מקיים רבי יוסי לחדשיו יבכר? u'mah
mekayem Rabbi Yosi l'chadashav yivaker? What does it mean its months, plural?
בכל חודש וחודש יהיה מבכר B'chol chodesh v'chodesh yihiyeh meivaker every month.
Doesn't mean two months per tree, every month. Okay. ועלהו לתרופה V'alehu
l'trufa its leaves will be used for healing, for medicine.
So,
רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, טרפי מצץ עלה וטרף מזונה. tarfei
matzitz aleh v'taraf mezona. So
it's its leaves, question whether to read this with a ת saf
or a ט. tes. Some want to read it טרף taraf with
a ט tes which means like food.
But the leaves will sort of sprout out on it and it
will be used for food, so וטרף v'taraf like with a ט.
tes. So meaning basically
you can even use the leaves for food. I don't know why
he has to reinterpret the פסוק. To use the fruit for food
and the leaves for medicine seems pretty good deal. Anyway, רב ושמואל,
Rav u'Shmuel, חד אמר chad amar now we go to do another
play on the word בתרופה. bi'trufa. להתיר פה. L'hatir peh. תרופה להתיר
פה. Trufa l'hatir peh. Okay. להתיר פה של מעלה L'hatir peh she'lemala
the mouth above, meaning it will make the mute be able to
speak. וחד אמר V'chad amar and the other says, להתיר פה של
מטה l'hatir peh she'lemata the mouth below, which says well could be
if you're constipated and so on, also says that it means if
you're barren, you make women fertile.
Okay, so תרופה להתיר פה. trufa l'hatir peh. אמר רבי חנינא ורבי
יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rabbi Chanina v'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, חד אמר
להתיר פה עקרות chad amar l'hatir peh akaros and now we have
it basically the parallel said more explicitly, barren women, וחד אמר להתיר
פה אילמים v'chad amar l'hatir peh ilmim mute people can speak. ולעומתם
בצד. u'le'umasam b'tzad.
Okay. So that was all elaborating on because we mentioned in the
south that the gate of the water was where the water will
eventually come out. So we had this whole discussion on the פסוקים
in יחזקאל. Now, without any, without any introduction, now for something completely
different, we go straight back to the משנה Mishnah about the about
the gates in the north. Okay. ולעומתם בצפון U'le'umasam b'tzafon and opposite
them you had the gates in the north.
It's a pretty like abrupt shift here.
By the way, interesting by the way that the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash, לעתיד לבוא l'asid lavo will be the center for a vegetarian
sustenance.
Thank you for that.
Yeah, I could say more but I won't.
Okay, you're fine. Okay. את מוצא בשעה שעלה נבוכדנצר לכאן At motza
b'shaa she'ala Nevuchadnezzar l'chan now we're going to talk about the שער
יכניה Sha'ar Yechanya where it says he went out when he went
into exile. So when נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar came up, בא וישב לו בדפני
של אנטוכיא. ba v'yashav lo b'dafni shel Antochia. He came and he
sat on the walls of Antioch. ויצאה סנהדרין גדולה לקראתו V'yatz'a Sanhedrin
Gedola likraso
so basically he was sitting there, I guess, plotting. and figuring out
the strategy for attacking ירושלים and the סנהדרין Sanhedrin went to greet
him, ואמרו לו, V'amru lo, and said to him, so it's an
interesting parallel to the stories of about smuggling out יוחנן בן זכאי
Yochanan ben Zakkai in the בית שני. bayis sheni. Here we have
the סנהדרין Sanhedrin going out in the בית ראשון. bayis rishon. Okay,
and what are they saying to him? They said to him: היזמן
הבית הזה ליחרב? He-izman ha-bayis ha-zeh le-hacharev?
You know what? It's time for the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, to
be destroyed. Go ahead, take care of it and go do it,
which is by the way again the parallel to יוחנן בן זכאי
Yochanan ben Zakkai who accepts the fate of what's about to happen
and plans for the future. אמר להן, Amar lahen,
so he said to them, אותו Oso or maybe they asked him,
you know, is it has it come? But it sounds like they're
telling him. אמר להן, Amar lahen, he said to them, אותו שהמלכתי
עליכם, Oso she-himlachti aleichem, the king that I made a king over
you, תנהו לי, Teneihu li, if you give him to me ואני
הולך, V'ani holech, I'll leave, so basically he, and which is actually
what happened, he deposed יכניה. Yechanya. He took him into exile. באו
ואמרו ליהויכין מלך יהודה, Bo v'amru l'Yehoyachin melech Yehuda, so they said
to יהויכין, Yehoyachin, נבוכדנצר בעי לך, Nevuchadnezzar ba'ei lach, oh
יהויכין, Yehoyachin, the principal wants you in his office! נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar wants
you. כיון ששמע מהן כן, Kivan she-shama me-hen ken, since he heard
this, נפל מפתחות של בית המקדש, nafal maftechos shel Beis HaMikdash, he
took the keys of the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, עלה לגגו של
היכל, alah l'gaga shel heichal, he went to the roof of the
היכל, heichal, אמר לפניו, Amar lefanav, and he said: רבונו של עולם,
Ribono shel Olam, Master of the Universe, לשעבר היינו נאמנים לך, l'she-avar
hayinu ne'emanim lach,
we were trustworthy to you, meaning we were entrusted with the בית
המקדש, we were entrusted with the keys. והיו מפתחותיך מסורים לנו, V'hayu
maftechotecha mesurim lanu, and your keys were given over to us. עכשיו
שאיננו נאמנים, Achshav she-einanu ne'emanim, now that we are no longer trusted
to you, הרי מפתחותיך מסורים לך. Harei maftechotecha mesurim lach. I am
giving you back your keys.
Is it a very cool metaphor?
I don't know. תרי אמוראים, Trei amora'im, so there's a debate of
אמוראים. amora'im. חד אמר, Chad amar,
one says, זרקן ועוד לא ירדו, zarkan ve-od lo yardu, he threw
them up and they have yet to come down.
They are on their way back down. What do you mean, maybe
they came down in the בית שני? Bayis Sheni? No, anyway, have
yet to come down.
Okay, where are we? חד אמר, Chad amar, and the other one
says, בא כמין יד ונטלתה מידו, ba k'min yad ve-natalta mi-yado,
a hand came out of heaven and took them back. You can
figure out the significance of the different interpretations. כיון
שראו, Kivan she-ra'u, once this was seen, כל חורי יהודה כן, kol
chorei Yehuda ken, all the... חורי יהודה, chorei Yehuda, assuming he means
בחורי יהודה? bachurei Yehuda?
How does it say what the word חורי chorei or אחורים achorim
means? בני חורין? Benei chorin? Nobles.
Nobles. Ah, okay. All the nobles of יהודה Yehuda came, עלו לראש
גגותיהן, alu l'rosh gagoseihen, they all went to their roof, ונפלו ומתו,
ve-naflu me-su, and they threw themselves off their roofs. הדא הוא דכתיב:
Hada hu d'chtiv: משא גיא חזיון מה לך אפוא כי עלית כולך
לגגות, massa gei chizayon mah lach eifo ki alisa kulech l'gagosei, what
is this that you have all gone up to the rooftops? תשואות
מלאה עיר הומיה, teshu'os m'le'ah ir homiyah,
the city is filled with tumult. So reading that this is what
happened in the time leading up to the חורבן הבית. Churban HaBayis.
Okay, so what are these דפני של אנטוכיא? Dofnei shel Antochia?
I assume it means that he was encamping in אנטיוכיה, Antiochos, you
know, in the city. Antioch? Yeah, I think so. Why is it
so far away? I know, so I don't know, they were just
trying to be preemptive. What does it say there? Antioch? אנטיוכיה, Antiochos,
it's a city.
Yeah. Well it
sounds like they were committing suicide. Yeah, I mean this is important
because there are a couple of מדרשים Midrashim where people throw themselves
off the roof, and that's brought up by the in the medieval
period by the חכמי אשכנז Chachmei Ashkenaz when they committed suicide during
the Crusades to show that as a type of legitimate religious expression.
You know, these מדרשים Midrashim
are significant in that whole discussion
around suicide. Okay, so let's try to get a little further now.
We get back to the next משנה. Mishnah. Okay, י"ג שולחנות, Yod
gimmel shulchanos, so as I already said, we did ABC, CBA, so
we did the השתחויה, Hishtachavaya, so now we do the tables. י"ג
שולחנות היו במקדש. Yod gimmel shulchanos hayu b'Mikdash. 13. שמונה של שיש
בבית המטבחיים, She-monah shel shayish b'veis hamitpachayim, eight made of marble
in the בית המטבחיים, beis hamitpachayim, literally, but what it really means
is the place where they would do the, well it says, שעליהם
מדיחים את הקרביים, she-aleihem medichim es hakirvayim, that's where they would wash
out the innards of the animals that they slaughtered and you know
get them out of all of the refuse that was in them,
so they would need these tables, and they were marble so the
meat would not spoil, it would keep the meat cold. ושתים במערב,
U-shtayim b'maarav,
two in the
west, הכבש אחד של שיש ואחד
של כסף, ha-kevesh echad shel shayish ve-echad shel kesef, one of
marble and one of silver. שיש נותנים את האיברים, Shayish nosnim es
ha-eivarim, on the marble one you would put the limbs that you
had to put up on the altar, and again you wanted them
to keep cold and not to begin to spoil. ושל כסף כלי
שרת, Ve-shel kesef klei shares, and the silver ones, that's where you
would keep the
vessels. Okay, that could look nice in silver, it didn't have to
be marble. ושתים באולם מבפנים על פתח הבית, U-shtayim ba-ulam mibifnim al
pesach habayis, two in the אולם ulam inside by the opening, by
the house, by you know when you go into the אולם ulam
right, if I show you the picture again here. Okay,
so
the two that were... במערב הכבש bemaarav hakevesh were on the west
of the ramp were here like you know can you see that
here? Two they were here, right, that's where they would keep the
what do you call it? That's where they would keep the pieces
of the animal and then they take them from there and bring
them up to the מזבח. mizbeach. That's on the west of the
ramp. These eight little squares up here are what they're calling the
בית המטבחיים, Beis HaMitbachayim, right over here. You see the can you
see the eight little squares there? That's where they would wash out
the innards, okay. And now here you go all of this is
open air, right, this part here, which is where you have the
שולחן shulchan and this was the קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kadashim, this was
all roofed over, and this first part was this אולם, ulam, was
the like you know the hall, you know the lobby. Okay, so
in this אולם ulam here you would have two. Okay and let's
take a look at what those two were.
Where's the where's the חיל? chel? The חיל?
chel? No the חיל chel is like a space outside
here outside the outermost wall.
Okay, okay.
בשני אולמות מבפנים על פתח הבית, Bishnei ulamot mibifnim al petach habayis,
one of marble ואחד של זהב, ve'echad shel zahav, one of gold.
על של שיש נותנים לחם הפנים בכניסתו. Al shel shayish notnim lechem
hapanim bichnisaso. Again you want it to be שיש shayish you don't
want it to be to start spoiling. Of course it's a little
different which is that you want the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim to
be hot, right, so okay we'll see about that. ועל של זהב
Ve'al shel zahav what? Miraculous anyway. Well that's what the גמרא is
going to say. You've anticipated the גמרא. ועל של זהב ביציאתו Ve'al
shel zahav biyetziaso and the gold one when you took the לחם
הפנים lechem hapanim out you you rested it on the gold one.
שמעלים בקודש ולא מורידין. Shemaalin bakodesh velo moridin. You go up in
sanctity so you want to go up from marble to silver. אחד
של זהב מבפנים שעליו לחם הפנים תמיד. Echad shel zahav mibifnim she'alav
lechem hapanim tamid. Oh and by the way did we forget to
mention there was also another שולחן shulchan out of gold that was
that was in the תורה Torah that they put the לחם הפנים
lechem hapanim on? Of the twelve thirteen שולחנות shulchanos one of them
was the one that we know as the שולחן של בית המקדש.
Shulchan shel Beis HaMikdash. Okay so let's take a look at the
גמרא. תני של כסף. Tani shel kesef. So על של כסף. al
shel kesef. So we have a ברייתא Beraisa that instead of saying
של שיש shel shayish says that it was on silver. Okay so
so meaning that that the what do you call it? The bread
was not put on a marble table on the way in, it
was put on a silver table on the way in. So רבי
יוסי בשם רבי שמואל בר רב יצחק רבי חנינא מתני בה בשם
רבי יוחנן לית כאן של כסף. Rabbi Yosei beshem Rabbi Shmuel bar
Rav Yitzchak, Rabbi Chanina masni bah beshem Rabbi Yochanan, leis kan shel
kesef. No they did not use silver. מפני שהוא מרתיח mipnei shehu
martiach because that would cause the bread to you know to get
too hot and it would and it would spoil. Okay some have
some say he says some have a different גרסא. girsa. It wasn't
marble because it would cause it to cool down, but our גרסא
girsa he says it wouldn't be silver because it would cause it
to get too hot and it would spoil. So the גמרא says
one minute, says everybody said that there aren't there enough נסים nissim
going on here? Why do we have to worry about this? לא
כן תני Lo ken tani do we not say in a ברייתא
Beraisa זה אחד מן הנסים שנעשו בבית המקדש, zeh echad min hanissim
shenaasu beBeis HaMikdash, one of the miracles in the בית המקדש, כשם
שהיו מניחים אותו חם, keshem shehayu manichim oso cham, the same way
they would put the bread on the table it was hot, כך
היו מוציאים אותו חם, kach hayu motzi'im oso cham, they would take
it off hot a week later. שנאמר לשום לחם חם ביום הלקחו.
Shene'emar: Lasum lechem cham beyom hilakcho. Bread that was as hot as
the day as the day it was taken, meaning it was totally
fresh as the day it was baked, fresh bread. So if it's
already a miracle so what do you care if the table is
gold is silver or marble? You don't have to worry about that
stuff. So רבי יהושע בן לוי אומר אין מזכירין מעשה נסים. Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi omer, ein mazkirin maaseh nissim. You don't mention miracles.
What the בבלי Bavli says: אין סומכין על הנס. ein somchin al
hanes. It's
very nice that you talk about miracles. We have to do what
we have to do to you know in order to address the
real world issues. God wants to also do a miracle, that'll be
very nice. Okay, בעי קמי רבי אימי. Ba'ei kamei Rabbi Ami. They
asked of אימי. Ami. לא היה שם לחם מהו להניחו לשבת הבאה
Lo hayah sham lechem, mahu lehannicho leshabbos haba'ah? Let's say for some
bizarre reason it came one שבת Shabbos that they didn't have new
לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. Can you leave the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim
for another week? Have it stay there straight for two weeks. So
the פסוק says לחם הפנים לפני תמיד. lechem hapanim lefanai tamid. So
maybe although we know that it's supposed to only be there for
a week, maybe it can stay there straight for two weeks if
something happens. I don't know. אמר לון Amar lon he says to
us: כתיב ונתת על השולחן לחם פנים לפני תמיד, ksiv: venasata al
hashulchan lechem panim lefanai tamid, לחם פנים אפילו פסול, lechem panim afilu
pasul,
even invalid. So the question: what does it mean invalid? Does the
bread become invalid if it's left on the שולחן shulchan more than
a week? But his basic it's a little unclear, but his basic
answer is: yes you can leave it there, it has to be
לפני תמיד lefanai tamid even after the week is up, it can
be left there straight. ואין לו נותר. Ve'ein lo nosar.
There's no
like
no
נותר nosar
that applies. Presumably, right. Or right. Or I think someone quotes רמב"ם
Rambam as saying that. Yeah, there's no נותר. nosar. Well we already
know the idea that there was what do you call it? That
there was you know if you put a certain קרבן korban on
the top of the מזבח mizbeach it does not become נותר. nosar.
So if this is remains on the שולחן shulchan as well it
might be, but it uses the phrase here of פסול. So anyway
without so there's some question about what happens to the status of
the bread, but regardless it it can be left there straight. It
can't mold? What? Well okay what happens will happen. Okay wait wait
we are finishing to the דף. daf. עשרה שולחנות עשה שלמה. Asarah
shulchanos asah Shlomo. Now שלמה Shlomo made ten שולחנות shulchanos not the
ones mentioned here. Ten that were duplicates of the שולחן הזהב. Shulchan
HaZahav. Okay, דכתיב *dichtiv*, ויעש שולחנות עשרה *vaya'as shulchanos asarah*, וינח בהיכל
חמישה מימין *vayanach baheichal chamisha miyamin*, two, four, five on the right,
וחמישה משמאל *vechamisha mismol*, and five on the left. אם תאמר חמישה
בדרום וה' בצפון *im tomar chamisha badarom ve-hei batzafon*, now right and
left as I told you would normally mean south and north because
you assume a person is facing east, so his right hand is
south and his left hand is north. So if you say it
means south and north, והלא אין השולחן כשר אלא בצפון *vehalo ein
hashulchan kasher ela batzafon*, that means that the actual שולחן *shulchan* that
is the real שולחן *shulchan* is in the middle of this line
of שולחנות *shulchanos* that's going from the north to the south, but
the שולחן *shulchan* is supposed to be the northernmost. It can't have
these other fake שולחנות *shulchanos* between it and the wall, שנאמר ואת
השולחן תתן על צלע צפון *shenemar ve'es hashulchan titein al tzela tzafon*.
So how can you say that, so what does, how can you
have other שולחנות *shulchanos* more northernmost than it? אלא מה תלמוד לומר
חמישה מימין וחמישה משמאל *ela mah talmud lomar chamisha miyamin vechamisha mismol*?
So what does it mean on the right and the left? אלא
חמישה מימין שולחנו של משה וחמישה משמאלו *ela chamisha miyamin shulchano shel
Moshe vechamisha mismolo*. It doesn't mean north and south, it means to
the right and the left of the שולחן *shulchan*. So it means
basically to the east and the west. The שולחן *shulchan* was in
the middle. They were on its right and its left if you
were facing the שולחן *shulchan*, but not north and south, rather east
and west. אף על פי כן לא היה מסדר אלא בשל משה
בלבד *af al pi chein lo hayah mesader ela beshel Moshe bilvad*.
And even though there were these ten שולחנות *shulchanos*, they only put
it on the one of משה *Moshe* בלבד *bilvad*, שנאמר את השולחן
אשר עליו לחם הפנים *shenemar es hashulchan asher alav lechem hapanim*. Okay,
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר *Rabbi Yosi be'Rabbi Yehudah omer*, על כולן
היה מסדר *al kulan hayah mesader*, which is like shocking. What, they
bake extra לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim*? שנאמר את השולחנות ועליהם לחם הפנים
*shenemar es hashulchanos va'alehem lechem hapanim*. So it's actually quite shocking and
the גמרא *Gemara* doesn't even discuss it. I mean you read these
פסוקים *pesukim*, you say what the heck is שלמה *Shlomo* doing adding
more vessels right to the, I mean it's one thing, you maybe
make the houses, what sort of things you do to the actual
structure, but the תורה *Torah* seems to be very מקפיד *makpid* on
certain particular types of vessels and to be making these replicas, so
it's one thing to be making the replicas, then the גמרא *Gemara*
sort of exacerbates it by saying they were doing all this whole
separate עבודה *avodah* and they put more, more bread on these tables.
It's quite shocking. It's not even really analyzed. Okay, so we'll wrap,
we'll continue with the גמרא *Gemara* tomorrow. My question was? Yeah, yeah.
No, no, no, it's by שלמה *Shlomo*.